Check the Migration Guide under Tutorials to learn how to get the most out of new features and update your worksheets to the latest version.
Choose Help > Tutorials or Help > QuickSheets to open live Mathcad worksheets and learn the best ways to use Mathcad.
Choose Tools > Worksheet Options to apply settings for compatibility with older versions and to change unit system defaults.
To see higher precision on any result, double-click the result to access the result Format dialog. On the Number Format tab, adjust the number of decimal places.
To display substitutions without a final numeric result, use the "explicit" symbolic keyword. 
For help on a function, click on the function name and press [F1].
To recalculate a region, click in the region and press [F9]; to recalculate the entire worksheet, press [Ctrl] [F9].
Mathcad indexes vectors starting with 0 by default. To start indexing at 1, go to Tools > Worksheet Options > Built-in Variables and change ORIGIN to 1.
PTC provides 24 hours a day technical support seven days a week in nine languages through its Web site, www.ptc.com/support/
For a list of built-in functions with descriptions, choose Insert > Function.
For a list of built-in units, with their associated quantity, choose Insert > Unit.
To evaluate an expression numerically, use the = key. For a symbolic result, press [Ctrl] [Period] for the -> operator.
To quickly plot a function, type the function using any unassigned letter as the independent variable. Then click the x-y plot button in the Graph toolbar and press [Enter].
To use non-multiplicative units, such as degrees Celsius or dB, use the postfix operator when defining quantities, and type the unit scaling function in the units placeholder.
To change the units in which a plot is displayed, divide the argument on the plot by the units in which you want it plotted.
Information about customer support, licensing, maintenance, and technical support for Mathcad can be found in the Customer Service Guide on the PTC Web site at http://www.ptc.com/support/cs_guide/.
To change the displayed alignment of an output table, right-click on the upper-left corner of the table and choose Alignment.
To import data permanently into a Mathcad worksheet, create an Input Table. Choose Insert > Data > Table, right-click on the upper-left corner, then choose Import.
Choose Help > Reference Tables for hundreds of standard tables for formulas and constants.
You can access Mathcad example files and all of your installed E-books from the Resources toolbar. To display the toolbar, click View > Toolbars > Resources.
To expand nested array notation in a matrix result, double-click on the result to access the Result Format dialog. On the Display Options tab,  enable "Expand nested arrays."
To apply a calculation to each element of a vector or matrix individually, use the vectorize operator.
Toolbars are a handy way to insert programming and symbolic keywords, or any of a large array of operators or Greek letters.
You can create your own functions in C or C++ and use them in Mathcad. Refer to the Developer's Reference (Help > Developer's Reference) for information about creating a user-DLL.
To insert buttons, text boxes, sliders, and other controls into your Mathcad worksheets, choose Insert > Control.
To enlarge the selection in an expression, press [Space].
To create a spreadsheet-like table of numbers, click in a blank part of your worksheet and choose Insert > Data > Table.
Many functions and operators that accept scalar arguments also accept vector arguments for performing an operation on many scalars at once.
To select any region with the dashed selection rectangle, click on the region while holding down the [Ctrl] key.
To nudge many regions at once drag across them to select them, then use the arrow keys to move them left, right, up, or down.
To move down from an exponent press [Space] or the right arrow.
For help on a particular menu item, press [Shift] [F1], then click the menu item.
Choose Help > QuickSheets to access example worksheets demonstrating analyses and tasks frequently performed in Mathcad.
Try the Programming Tutorial under Features In-Depth (located in the Tutorials) for tips on setting up and using programming keywords.
To select a string variable, click in the string and use the right arrow key to move the vertical selection cursor just to the right of the last pair of quotes.
To display a result in binary, octal, or hexadecimal, double-click on the result to access the Result Format dialog. On the Display Options tab, change the Radix setting. Use b, o, or h after the number.
When you type a word and press [Space], Mathcad starts a text region for you.
To type a Greek letter, type the Roman equivalent and then press [Ctrl] g to change it to Greek. To type the Greek letter pi, type p [Ctrl] g.
To format numeric results as fractions or mixed numbers, click Format > Result. To format only one specific result, double-click the result.
You can communicate with other Mathcad users through Mathcad's online User Forums. Choose Help > User Forums.
To move out of the denominator of a fraction, press [Space].
You can insert or delete lines by right-clicking in a blank area of your worksheet and pressing [Insert] or [Delete].
For help on an error message, press [F1] while the message is displayed.
To bring data in from a data file, use the File Read or Write component by choosing Insert > Component.
To undo a sequence of editing changes in a math region, press [Ctrl] z.
To shift the insertion bar from one side of a selected expression to the other, press [Insert].
To quickly delete a region, click on it and press [Ctrl] d or choose Edit > Delete.
To evaluate a derivative symbolically, fill in the derivative operator and press [Ctrl] [Period].
To assign a numeric function to a symbolic result, just type the definition symbol at the front of the symbolic evaluation, and make any undefined variables arguments to the new function.
When editing math check the status messages at the bottom left of the screen for helpful suggestions.
To delete an operator, place the cursor between the operator and the operand. Press [Delete] to remove an operator to the right or [Bksp] to remove an operator to the left.
You can create a new line within the same paragraph in a text region by typing [Shift] [Enter]. To create a new line in a new paragraph, type [Enter].
You can make a text region occupy the entire width of a page. Right-click the region, click Properties, and select "Occupy Page Width" on the Text tab.
To set up an equation for a symbolic solution, use [Ctrl] = to insert the bold (Boolean) equals sign.
The Mathcad User's Guide is available in PDF form from the Resources window.
You can display any matrix as a grayscale image by typing its name and choosing Insert > Picture. Since displayed pixel values correspond to gray levels between 0 and 255, you should scale the matrix.
Mathcad has two kinds of subscripts. To identify the element in row 3 of the vector x, type x[3. For literal subscripts, use a period instead of [.
You can refer to a built-in unit or function name, even after you have redefined the name, using the Namespace operator. Type [Ctrl] [Shift] n after the variable name, then type unit for the built-in unit namespace, or mc for the built-in Mathcad function names.
Enabling lighting on a 3D plot can drastically change its color. For best results, set the fill color to white.
To change the units in an answer from the default, click on the answer, then click on the placeholder to the right of the answer and type the name of the new unit.
When pasting an object into Mathcad from another application, choose Edit > Paste Special to specify the type of object you are pasting.
Mathcad's default unit for angle measure is radians. To find the sine of 3 degrees, type sin(3*deg)=.
To turn an answer in radians into degrees, type deg in the placeholder to the right of the answer.
To apply a function or operation to a vector or matrix of values element-wise, use [Ctrl] [-]. This puts the vectorize arrow over the expression.
To completely hide one or more regions in your worksheet, use a collapsed area. Then set the area properties so that there is no name, icon, border, or timestamp on the area.
Scalar and vector answers can be copied and pasted just like any other expression. Just select the result and choose Edit > Copy.
To find the abbreviation for a unit, choose Insert > Unit and look in the Insert Unit dialog.
You can pull in functions and variables defined in other worksheets. Choose Insert > Reference and specify a worksheet. The contents of that worksheet are used where you inserted the reference.
When you animate a 2D plot, first fix the axis limits by entering your own values in the four axes-limit placeholders. This prevents the plot from rescaling the axes during the animation. 
Variables definitions inside a Mathcad program are known only inside the program. However, a program uses the values of any variables defined above or to the left of the program in your worksheet.
You can find and/or replace typographical characters using the Find and Replace dialogs. Enter ^t for a tab, ^p for a Return, ^l for a line break, and ^\ for a backslash.
Greek and other extended characters supported by a Unicode font are allowed in the Find and Replace dialogs. You can enter these characters with either the appropriate keyboard, or by pasting them from another application. Also, you can enter Greek characters by typing the Roman equivalent, followed by [Ctrl] g.
If you want to keep a region from calculating, right-click in the region and choose Disable Evaluation. A small box appears to the right of the equation to indicate that it is disabled.
There are three different "equals" signs in Mathcad. Press = to get a numerical answer. Press : to define a variable. To state that two quantities are equal, use [Ctrl] = to insert a Boolean equals sign for equations you want to solve.
To integrate the data set sampled at irregularly spaced points, use interpolation. Define f(t) := linterp(x,y,t) and then use the numerical integration operator to integrate f.
To deselect one of a group of selected regions, press [Ctrl] and click on the region to deselect.
To print out these tips, locate the file mtips_EN.txt in your Mathcad folder and open it in a text editor. Be careful to not alter the contents of the file.
To create a 3D QuickPlot, enter a 2-variable function, then type the name of that function without its variables as the argument in a 3D plot.
You can select multiple regions and change properties common to all of the regions selected, rather than changing each region separately.
If you want to restrict user access to a small number of regions in your worksheet, you can opt to protect your worksheet, rather than inserting areas and locking them. Choose Tools > Protect Worksheet.
To read data from files interactively, choose Insert > Data > File Input. You can then select a subset of rows and columns that can be recalculated by clicking on it and pressing [F9].
You can define a variable by the result of a numerical evaluation in a single line. This allows you to capture the output of a function that is defined numerically and then evaluate it symbolically.
To change the properties of a File Input component, such as the file to read, right-click on the component.
To select a single region, hold down the [Shift] key and click on it. Repeating this action undoes the selection.
You can type the name and path of any JPEG, BMP, GIF, or TIFF image into a string variable in the placeholder of a picture operator to display the image. Both grayscale and color images are supported.
You can output a matrix of pixel values selected in a picture operator. Right-click on the picture and set the desired limits on the Properties tab.
To animate any equation or graph in Mathcad, make the values dependent on the built-in FRAME variable (default is 0), then choose Tools > Animation > Record, and select the regions you wish to animate.
The default units returned for any value are dependent on the unit system chosen. To change unit systems, choose Tools > Worksheet Options and select from the choices on the Unit System tab.
Assigning the largest index element of a matrix first will speed matrix calculations
If you are manipulating many large matrices in a calculation, but only need to use the values of the last one, assign the intermediate matrices in a program. These will not be saved in memory after the program is run.
Solve block results can be parameterized on any value, including guess values, equation variables, conditional constraints, or initial conditions. A parameterized output can be used within a program to run the solve block repeatedly.
You can use the WRITEPRN and APPENDPRN functions in a program by passing them both the name of the file to write to and the data values to be written as a second argument.
You can apply a vectorized function or operator to a vector and evaluate the result numerically or symbolically. To apply the vectorize operator, type the function, then type [Ctrl][-]to insert the vectorize operator, which is displayed as an arrow above the function.
To reduce the size of your files, you can store images as lower quality JPEGs. To do so, open the XML options in the Properties dialog under the File menu.